[SPEAKER_00]: So, I thought we could talk about craving, which is a central theme in Buddhism.
[SPEAKER_00]: And we've obviously spoken about it a lot, but making sure that one is clear on that can't be harmful, even if you've been doing it, trying to practice for a while, just to make sure you're on the right path.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know,
[SPEAKER_00]: One can understand what craving is in an abstract manner, but sometimes you can get confused, like, you know, where is it actually?
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, someone might be trying to find it, trying to actually see it, trying to, you know, dedicating themselves to get rid of craving, but where is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: How is it?
[SPEAKER_00]: Where can I find it?
[SPEAKER_00]: And, you know, just to just go over the basic definition in the suttas, it says, the cause of suffering is craving, which makes for further being, accompanied by delight and lust, which rejoices here and there.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, craving for sensual pleasure, craving for being, craving for non-being, is the cause of suffering.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, well, yeah, so when it says craving for... craving for being, it does not refer to like a metaphysical future in a sort of like a... like a...
[SPEAKER_01]: Being on the level of, you know, like what... what philosophies are trying to decipher what is a being and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, it includes that, for sure, but it really refers to the quite a practical way of...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it says when the continuation of being, in other words, it's just like saying a continuation of your is-ness, the way you are,
[SPEAKER_01]: The way your tendencies are, the way your pressures are, so craving fuels the continuation of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, of course, that goes, reaches the metaphysics and reaches the whole, like, future and everything else that would come as a result of still being the way you are now.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, the craving that's maintaining that, is the craving towards sensuality, sensual desires, sensual objects, craving towards being, craving towards non-being.
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, craving towards, eh... isness of certain things, presence of certain things, and then craving for the absence of certain other things.
[SPEAKER_01]: You don't want them to be.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, eh... it's that craving that maintains those pathways and those domains.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not like, as I said, it's not like a craving for some abstract idea of being and who I am and my identity.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a lot more palpable, like maintenance of your addictions, maintenance of your dependencies, maintenance of your false securities that you find in sense objects, environment and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's what the being is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, that's why you start
[SPEAKER_01]: Uprooting that craving, or restraining that craving, you're going to start feeling unsafe.
[SPEAKER_01]: You're going to start feeling threatened, anxious and so on, because you are undoing that which you are.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's not going to feel pleasant, initially at least, until, like, you know, the right view is developed and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: When then you start recognizing, you know, that's actually the true safety and true liberation, undoing of all being.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if I want to destroy craving,
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, I keep the precepts, central strength, and I sit down and I want to destroy craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: Where do I...?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yes, you don't... you can't just destroy craving as an object that you can find and then just smash it.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can unscrew it, put it that way.
[SPEAKER_01]: You can't just pull it out, get rid of it, but you could go around it in a correct manner, that would result in fundamental, complete unscrewing of that craving from your experience, removal.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, yeah, you could be thinking and pondering about it all you want and trying to understand and see and abstract, basically, dwell in abstract concepts of what craving is.
[SPEAKER_01]: But practically, that craving is that which is manifested through your actions by body, speech and mind.
[SPEAKER_01]: Through your intentions, they would be rooted in craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, whenever you act out, you are maintaining, you are giving into the craving, you are maintaining the being.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whenever you act by body, by speech, mentally, you are very much fueling.
[SPEAKER_01]: The dependencies, the craving, and everything else that follows.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you want to stop acting out of craving...
[SPEAKER_01]: Sorry, you want to uproot, you want to overcome the craving, you want to remove it from your experience, you have to stop engaging in any types of experience that are based on it, that stem from it, that are fueled by it, and that fuel it more in return.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in order to extinguish the fire, you have to remove its fuel.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to completely deplete it of anything burnable.
[SPEAKER_01]: Anything that can serve and susceptible to burn, you actually need to abandon, remove, protect from coming back into the fire and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's how fire will eventually completely go out.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do I know that I'm actually doing that?
[SPEAKER_00]: If I say, okay, well, lust, aversion, distraction, those are based on craving to get rid of suffering.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I act out of lust, I act out of aversion, I distract myself.
[SPEAKER_00]: But when I stop doing that,
[SPEAKER_00]: There's still tension.
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, yeah, there's still fire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do I know that I'm actually diminishing this fire of craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, initially, you probably won't have an immediate reference point.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, you need to use your intelligence and intellect to arrive at the conclusion that certain types of actions are more likely to result in diminishing of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not a really
[SPEAKER_01]: Astrophysics or neuroscience, you just need to be honest with yourself, sit down and see which is more likely to increase the thirst, desire, craving, pressure, and which is more likely to decrease it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Which types of action, which courses of my intentions that I follow would result in accumulation, intensification of the fire, and which ones would result in diminishing of it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, so it's not the fire that you just started yesterday.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's a fire that's been burning for who knows how long and packed with fuel and burnable materials.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, once you stop adding more, yes, that's the obviously the first and the necessary step, but then you also have to now wait, make sure no new things come into it and then wait, basically, that things that are already under fire burn.
[SPEAKER_01]: That has to be depleted to some extent.
[SPEAKER_01]: How long do you have to wait?
[SPEAKER_01]: In other words, how long do you have to endure that internal fire that's going to get amplified when you stop adding more fuel to it?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, that depends on how big the fire was, how passionate your actions were, how much... how infected they were with greed, aversion, distraction, hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's not going to disappear overnight.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, obviously, if you recognize that the key is to not add new fuel to your existing fire, to not increase that,
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, yeah, patience, patient endurance, khanti, as the suttas would describe, and that's pretty much the training in virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's the sole purpose of virtue.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, there are secondary benefits of virtue in the suttas that the Buddha would talk about, but the real main benefit is exactly, like, preventing any more careless, ignorant adding of the fuel to the fire of craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: containing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, as the fire lessens, the clearer... well, the picture becomes clearer as to what's really happening, where the real issue is.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, obviously, with the understanding, it will be even easier to not add more fuel.
[SPEAKER_01]: It will be even easier to prevent the careless, accidental additions of fuel to that craving, because, obviously, you're becoming more and more transparent, and you recognize those those risks, those dangers, way before you even engage with them.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, having having faith in that basic reasoning, that's, you know, if I... Well, having faith in the basic reasoning, just so that you can start doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Just so that you can start training in the precepts.
[SPEAKER_00]: But eventually, one can expect that that fire will diminish and you will experience... Of course.
[SPEAKER_01]: ...diminishment.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, obviously, what's going to happen is, the fire might start diminishing right away.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the thing is, when you're in the fire, it burns equally.
[SPEAKER_01]: Doesn't matter how big it is.
[SPEAKER_01]: So you don't have a reference to how much the old fire burnt more, because currently you're still burnt.
[SPEAKER_01]: So that's why people would sometimes give up or lose faith, because they expect that external reference point to show them how much fire has diminished.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it factually is diminishing, but as I said, all you have there and then, when the craving is present, is the burn of the craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it just feels like that same craving is always there.
[SPEAKER_01]: However, if certain other things prompt you, like certain memories, certain circumstances prompt you and you get reminded,
[SPEAKER_01]: Of how much worse it used to be, that's when you realize, oh, actually, quite a lot of fire has diminished.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you encounter something that used to make you act in a certain way, and you you couldn't control yourself.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you stopped, you withdraw yourself from it, you spent, like, you know, decent amount of time restraining, contemplating the right things, everything we talk about.
[SPEAKER_01]: Obviously, when the craving arises, it still hurts, like, the same way, the pressure, the desire.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, sometimes, accidentally, you just stumble upon something, you see, hear, smell, taste, touch something that used to... you remember vividly the extent of provocation that that would cause, and now you realize, oh, my mind didn't even move.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or didn't even move the tenth of what it used to move.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then you recognize, oh, yeah, from one point of view, presence of craving means, yes, there is always going to be a degree of that burn for as long as I'm not truly free, which is exactly what can motivate you to go all the way to the freedom.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then, on the other hand, you actually do get a glimpse into the perspective that shows you, like, oh, actually, there is a difference now.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, in terms of the intensity, in terms of the pressure, in terms of the ability to contain it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, yeah, you cannot have that reference point equally present all the time, like some sort of lighthouse always showing you, because obviously you are within that craving.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's why you have to keep reminding yourself of the values, maintaining the context.
[SPEAKER_01]: You have to work your way out from the inside, in other words.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's what the Buddha meant when he said you can't... you can't measure your progress, like, in the same sense that a carpenter who uses his axe cannot measure every day how much of his axe handle has worn out.
[SPEAKER_01]: But he knows that through sticking through it, i.e.
[SPEAKER_01]: through using the handle, it is wearing out.
[SPEAKER_01]: I can't say this much today and this much it will wear tomorrow.
[SPEAKER_01]: But the time will come when one day I'll pick it up and realize, oh, my handle's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to replace it.
[SPEAKER_01]: And that's exactly the same with the craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can get a sense that it's wearing out.
[SPEAKER_01]: You could get even a recognition, as I said, if something reminds you.
[SPEAKER_01]: But overall, you recognize that, no, only when it's gone, I can know that it's gone.
[SPEAKER_01]: Until then, I'm still doing the same work.
[SPEAKER_01]: I'm still using it the same way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And I was thinking of another, like, you know, you can think to yourself,
[SPEAKER_00]: I have been suffering, I want to end suffering, my suffering, and in what ways have I tried to do that?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, my whole life, have I ever tried to give up craving?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, have I ever even attempted to go in this direction?
[SPEAKER_01]: I've finally done it, by the way.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, and I've been doing it for so long, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, have I even considered, have I even considered, have I even attempted, genuinely, to go in the other direction?
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if this other direction, which is non-craving, is... doesn't work, well, there is then... what other direction is there?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because I've gone the other way.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now I'm trying non-craving.
[SPEAKER_00]: That doesn't work well.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do I have to lose?
[SPEAKER_01]: Training.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, I've got the dukkha already.